<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>At the Mountains of Madness</title><link href="http://miskatonic.ged.msu.edu/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://miskatonic.ged.msu.edu/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://miskatonic.ged.msu.edu/</id><updated>2014-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>the interesting thing about trans women and science and Science</title><link href="http://miskatonic.ged.msu.edu/interesting.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Camille Scott</name></author><id>tag:miskatonic.ged.msu.edu,2014-07-17:interesting.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a rather unsavory series of comments from one of the editors of Science
Careers, and the twitter storm that followed, I've been motivated to write. First,
the background. Science recently ran a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/345/6193.toc#SpecialIssue"&gt;special issue&lt;/a&gt; on Strategies against HIV/AIDS. The cover of this issue depicts several transgender sex workers, from
the neck down, in revealing clothing, along with a blurb about high risk groups. Cue Jim Austin and his
twitter comments. Let's begin with one to set the tone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Interesting to consider how those gazey males will feel when they find out.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; -- Jim Austin, &amp;#64;SciCareerEditor&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting is the operative word of the day. Given that this was in response to the pictured
womens' trans status, perhaps Mr. Austin thinks it's &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; how often trans women
are raped, assaulted, and murdered because of such men &amp;quot;finding out.&amp;quot; Or
perhaps it's more &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; to observe the casual transphobia displayed by men in positions
of privilege like himself. After all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You realize they are transgender? Does it matter? That at least colors things, no?&lt;/em&gt; -- Jim Austin, &amp;#64;SciCareerEditor&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why yes, it does color things, and in very &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; ways. There is a long and
very colorful history of the relationship between trans people and scientists.
We could consider that scientists
who found trans women &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; in the 70's and 80's helped set back trans rights by decades.
We could consider that scientists who found trans women &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; created a conception of
trans women being shallow and manipulative by writing as such in their articles, because trans women
were only okayed for treatment by those same scientists if they acted out those stereotypes.
We could consider that scientists
and lawyers who found trans women &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; created a healthcare system that, for decades, made it
almost impossible for trans women to get treatment. We could consider that
scientists who find trans women &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt; have continually used us as lab rats to
publish poorly-supported sexist conclusions on the differences between gendered brains,
with no visible knowledge gain given back to the trans community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or for things our esteemed editor might consider less &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;, we could consider that actions
like the recent one only further the common conception that trans women of color
are good for nothing but satisfying the sexual desires of men (but make sure we call it &amp;quot;raising
awareness&amp;quot; so people can think this reinforcement is noble). We could consider that many
trans women are denied careers in fields like, say, science, because of these
stereotypes. Or we could consider that many trans women are denied careers outright because
of these stereotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I haven't even talked about the cover yet! I'm not sure I need to; it's been discussed
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scientopia.org/blogs/drugmonkey/2014/07/16/does-science-magazine-actually-sell-many-copies-at-the-newsstand/"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt; quite nicely.
But I can talk about trans representation in science, and even in Science. How about instead
of once again pointing out the public health concerns of trans sex workers, we have a special issue
on the pressures that force so many trans women into sex work in the first place? Or on
the false notions of LGBT people being the root cause of sexually transmitted diseases?
Or, a special issue of articles written by only trans scientists?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not your lab rats. We are not your charitable tax writeoff. We are not your
fetish objects. We &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; scientists, we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; mothers, we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; students, teachers,
lawyers, doctors, sex workers, dock workers, factory workers, social workers,
musicians, artists. We are people. And we are more than &amp;quot;interesting.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Camille&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="trans"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="sexism"></category><category term="trigger-warning"></category></entry><entry><title>Welcome to the Madness</title><link href="http://miskatonic.ged.msu.edu/the-first-post.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-09-02T01:36:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Camille Scott</name></author><id>tag:miskatonic.ged.msu.edu,2013-09-02:the-first-post.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Mountains of Madness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, you might ask, are we at the Mountains of Madness?
To begin, I'll provide a quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics is like being slowly bitten to death by ants.&lt;/em&gt; --&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog"&gt;C. Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend some time trying to assemble a highly polymorphic genome, or fumbling around
the NCBI database, and you'll understand why we're at the Mountains of Madness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all seriousness, this blog is intended to be about bioinformatics, and my work
in it. I am a second-year PhD student at Michigan State University, working in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ged.msu.edu"&gt;GED Lab&lt;/a&gt; under Titus Brown.
When we're not exploring the Mountains of Madness, hoping the Old Ones will provide insights
into assembly or reveal to us better probabilistic data structures, our lab spends a
lot of time discussing the utility of maintaining an online presence in science; this is
my foray into that realm! With any luck, I hope to update regularly. Aside from the obvious
benefits of networking with others in the field and staking my claim in the research world,
a blog has the secondary benefit of giving a set goal to work toward -- having something
concrete to write about in a semi-formal way, on a semi-monthly or more basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To kick things off, a post on my recent experience at the Marine Biological Lab will be coming soon!
I'll talk about some lessons learned, my thoughts on teaching computational skills to biologists,
and provide a small exercise in assembly that we used. Until then,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Camille&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="introduction"></category><category term="first"></category></entry></feed>